Docker architecture.
Docker architecture is client server type.
There are just two things which is Docker client,
also known as Docker CLI and Docker server.
This Docker server is also known by another name
as Docker demon or Docker.
So coming to the next,
we see this whole architecture of Docker.
This is the client and this is the Docker demon or Docker server.
So the Docker client will send these commands
to these Docker demon and the Docker demon will execute
these commands.
We run this commands from the command prompt of windows
or the terminal of Linux.
Once these commands are run,
the client will take these commands to the Docker demon
and the Docker demon will execute these commands.
These commands can be creating images, containers,
and doing other things like Docker,
pull commands, Docker, build, Docker run,
are different types of commands.
We will understand more about commands,
the containers images later on.
Now we will understand Docker image.
A Docker image is a template for running containers.
For example, Microsoft.net is provided as a Docker image.
Similarly, Microsoft SQL server is also provided
as a Docker image.
Our Docker images could be engine X, web server,
post-grads SQL, red days, PHP and Python,
etcetera, etcetera. We can create a Docker image
for our app on.net, version 10,
based on newborn to OS along with engine X, web server.
We can create another image of our app on version.net 9.0,
which is based on Windows OS along with engine X, web server.
So these can be two images.
Similarly, dear could be many more images of our app.
So let us understand how images are built.
So images are built on layers.
And there are many layers in an image.
For example, there is a base OS image,
which could be a Linux or a Windows or Mac OS.
And then there could be another layer of runtime,
which could be.net runtime, version.net 10,
or runtime.net 9, etcetera.
There could be dependencies, which our app needs.
These could be JSON.net package or the entity framework,
code package, etcetera, etcetera.
And application code is our.net app,
which we have built and configuration files
could be the another image layer
for the configuration files of our app.
Images are very lightweight and very fast
because they are built on layers.
When we do some changes on them,
then only the layers that have changed are be rebuilt,
rest remains the same.
This makes the image lightweight and very fast.
To build an image,
we will need to have a Docker file,
which is a text file,
providing all the instructions needed for the image to build.
Let us see the Docker file of a.net version 10 app.
So this is the Docker file.
Each instruction here will create a layer.
For example, this instruction from mcr.microsoft.com,
etcetera will create a layer.
Another instruction is this one.
This will also create a layer.
And this third will also create a layer.
Similarly, the fourth one will also create a layer.
Docker file will also refer to external files
and libraries needed for the app to run.
For example, it is referring to SDK version 10 of.net
and ASP.net version 10.
It can also refer to other dependencies like newtons of JSON
or entity framework or needed for the app to run,
all will be listed on this Docker file.
So when the image was built,
it will download these dependencies
so that the app can run Docker container.
A Docker container is an object that runs the images.
For example, these are the images
and Docker container will be needed to run them.
A Docker container could be running.net image.
Another Docker container could be running MS SQL Server image.
Another Docker container could be running engine X image,
Redis image, etcetera, etcetera.
We have Docker commands for creating containers,
running containers, deleting containers and so on.
Docker registries.
Registries store Docker images online
so that people can download these Docker images
of software's ARMD's registries.net image
and MS SQL image, engine X image, etcetera,
all kept on Docker registries.
Example of these registries are Docker hub
and Azure container registry.
On Google type Docker hub
and click on the search result.
Here we can search microsoft.
These are the Microsoft images of different products.
You will find MS SQL Server image here.
Then here are other images,
including the dot net image needed for our dot net app to build.
So you can also create an account here
and you can save your app images on Docker Hub.
Other than that,
you can also search for is your container registry.
You can create account on Azure to use these container registry.
We can understand the whole process from this image.
Programmer a creates a dot net image for his app
and pushes this image to Docker hub registry.
Programmer B now wants to download this image
from this Docker hub registry
and she can easily download the image
and the image reaches her own local laptop
and she can create a container of this image
and run the dot net app
which is produced by Programmer A.